welcome to untangling the world knot of
consciousness
wrestling with the hard problems of mind
and meaning in the modern scientific age
my name is john verviki i'm a cognitive
psychologist and cognitive scientist at
the university of toronto in canada
throughout the entire series i will be
joined in dialogue by my good friend and
colleague
greg enriquez from james madison
university in the united states
throughout we are going to wrestle with
the hard problems of how we can give an
account
of a phenomenal like consciousness
within
the scientific worldview how we can
wrestle with that problem in conjunction
with the problem that greg calls the
problem of psychology
that is pervasive throughout psychology
which is that psychology has no unified
descriptive metaphysics
by which it talks about mind and or
behavior
throughout this we will be talking about
some of the most important philosophical
cognitive scientific and neuroscientific
accounts of consciousness
so i hope you'll join us throughout
we've done three
um sessions so far um i took the lead on
those
in which i was trying to set up um the
problem
of what's typically called you know the
problem of consciousness the hard
problem of consciousness sometimes
more traditionally called the mind body
problem um and trying to show
how using the pivotal figure descartes
to try and show
how enmeshed this problem is
in our worldview our scientific world
view how they're deeply interwoven and
bound together
and how much they're enmeshed with our
our sense our normative sense of
realness and how that
and how that normative sense is actually
unstable for us
in a way that intersects with uh the
difficulty
of the heart problem of consciousness
and we want to continue that history but
we're going to shift and greg is going
to take the lead and i'll be more of the
interlocutor commentator um and
he's going to discuss how this
this world knot you know sort of
unfolded and ramified
through the history of psychology so
welcome greg and uh
great thank you for taking us through
this please amen
amen thank you great to be here uh look
forward to this uh installment i think
we have
set up what i want to share here very
well today
through the three previous installments
in particular
uh analyzing descartes struggles
uh with mind and matter okay
really sets up essentially the stage
which i'm going to then try to take
forward
following it in relationship to the
discipline of psychology
okay and what my fundamental
point here is that there is that i
really want uh
i think anybody that cares about
philosophy science uh knowledge the
social sciences
um should really understand is that
there is this thing called the problem
of psychology
okay um and that it's actually well
documented it's well understood
and in a nutshell here's the basic
problem and that is to this day
we don't have a good language system
a consensually agreed upon way of
talking
as professionals as experts as
scientists as philosophers
of the intersection of science
mind and behavior
okay we just we don't know we don't have
the shared
understanding of what those terms mean
as
reference in the world that's my basic
point
so greg would uh would it be fair to use
uh
koon's notion here of psychology being
pre-paradigmatic
that it doesn't have a unifying paradigm
science exactly so that's exactly so i
like to say that modern psychology
uh is both pre and multi-paradigmatic
okay and it's pre-paradigmatic in the
sense that it does not have
the classic consensual so we can use
newton's classic mechanics
as the ultimate paradigm that lasts 200
years in physics where
the idea of what matter was what the
foundational laws were
the calculus that we're going to use to
study it and the power of that paradigm
to dominantly allow
um consensual knowledge to be built with
a center
uh that for that has virtual um complete
agreement until
uh the anomalies of quantum mechanics
general relativity then sort of
overthrow that but
that's a classic example of paradigm and
what i'm going to walk through
is really psychology has never had a
paradigm
okay it is it very quickly
started to fragment um and then never
achieved any kind of dominance in
relationship to
what actually it was okay
so that's interesting um i agree with
that i think that's a
i remember uh talking to my friends
about this when i was in grad school
uh about this we read uh you know some
philosophy of science and [ __ ] at the
time
but i'm interested you've got a a more
subtle distinction
maybe you could unpack it just a little
bit you said psychology is
pre-paradigmatic and you've just
explained that
but i i don't want to steal your fender
for what you're going to say but in what
sense do you see
psychology as multi paradigmatic
right and that's that's a so now what we
will do in
in the sense that of course there are
clusters of ideas we have
freud and psychoanalysis and uh
psychodynamic thinking we have
behaviorism starting with watson uh and
so actually i'll use that opportunity
to help understand the different
paradigms uh that at least people tried
to establish
to then compete for dominance over what
this
territory is okay great
that's really good great one more
question and now i'm going to putting on
my cock's i hat
here and so there's also uh i mean
what the difficulties of course without
a paradigm or especially when you're
multi
paradigmatic is a massive ontological
equivocation and confusion
which of course you've highlighted in
some of your work um
and then i'm also thinking uh as a
cognitive scientist
that there's even that there's a
is this the right adjective there's a
even a broader uh possibility of the
qualification because there's also
competing
sciences of mind with psychology there's
neuroscience there's artificial
intelligence
i really believe okay so if we ask why
are we
why is the meaning crisis right now in
the 21st century particularly acute
okay and what is the way what are one of
the key patterns that we're going to
need to wake up from it
it is solving the language game problem
on this issue
okay and wittgenstein you know i use
that from him and i i
you know he hated psychology in many
ways because he saw it
as a convoluted mess rightfully so
so we're going to have multiple
paradigms inside the field
we're going to have competing
interacting elements associated with it
down into neuroscience okay and then
actually
up into philosophy of language issues
we're going to have cultural
and indigenous psychological problems
okay meaning problems in terms of will
what is the frame that you're actually
trying to place on so all what you get
what i realized i so so i i want to be
clear i love psychology okay i took
60 uh five credits as an undergrad i was
half of what i did
um and i was like oh my gosh you can do
a science of mine you can measure stuff
uh you can do experimentation um
and my journey on this is then i
actually got into the therapy world in
my graduate studies
okay uh and and i wasn't i wasn't aware
that there was a problem after 60
credits and relatively
you know reasonably thoughtful about
these issues it didn't really dawn on me
because what i thought psychology was
because this is what i was told
is that it's really it's about the
science that we're trying to do
okay so it's really about the
epistemology
and methodology that we're trying to
take that's actually what
modern psychology becomes okay is that
it's a frame
an epistemological methodological frame
called science
that we're going to apply okay and and
then but when you actually become a
therapist
all right and you start to say okay i'm
gonna be a clinical psychologist now i'm
gonna have to work
uh and then i learn stuff from the
modern cool psychodynamic from freud to
young
uh karen horneis one of my favorites you
know there are a lot of really
interesting stuff there
and then i learned the becky and model
and ellis and which is the cognitive
psychotherapy paradigm
and and then i i was always actually
most uh
arm wrestling with skinner although i
turn out that my model is about
if there's one person it turns out to be
parallel with it's actually ironically
about bf skinner of all peoples
interesting okay
so all of these individuals say really
interesting things
and then i wanted to be coherent as a
therapist i want to be grounded in
science and say
but when you back up you realize that
they actually use these very different
languages have very different starting
points
make very different claims and then you
get massive equivocation
when you try to achieve coherence right
okay
this is a very helpful and clear setup
greg so
start taking us through the history then
please okay so
the history is right where we left off
with descartes
and the emergence of modern science okay
so you what you have is from we'll do
the galileo
into newton and the development of
matter and motion
okay so just for clarity we are adopting
now a naturalistic
frame for cause and effect okay we're
gonna start
measuring stuff because we're now
suspicious of the representational mind
we're gonna try to cancel that out so
that we get independent
measurement of primary qualities and we
will be suspicious of the secondary
first person empirical perspective
qualities
and we're going to try to grain
systematic methods of experimentation
measurement and the mathematical mapping
of matter in motion
okay so so let's just route just so we
can keep refreshing people's awareness
of this term
so we can use it greg invoked the
distinction that's common to both
galileo
and descartes between primary and
secondary qualities the primary ones are
the mathematically measurable ones as
great just said and those secondary
qualities
right uh that exists only in some sense
in the representational mind
the the the term that is used for that
in
sort of common parlance or qualia so
when i'm talking when greg and i start
talking about qualia
we're talking about all of those
properties all of those qualities
that are not held by the scientific
worldview
to be properties of objective things but
exist in some sense
vague look at my hands waving it's only
only in the mind
just just to remind people of that
exactly
okay and then so and then we get the uh
the empiricist philosophers most
famously
lock and hume okay really saying well
what is this what are we seeing what's
out here
making this distinction refining it and
now
and and renee descartes coming along
with dualism
okay offering that split that there's
these there's the world of mind
there's the world of matter um we get
then we get uh kant with his
rational and empirical synthesis and
really is the modern
the founder you know modern philosophy
really begins with kant
okay and he then offers his categories
of mind he brings the idea of that
mind is not just a blank slate but it
actually has what we would call perhaps
cognitive schema
yeah that afforded the categories of
space and time and causality that are
built in
um and and he then has i don't want to
get into the technical aspects of the a
priori synthetic whatever
but there's basically okay the mind
the human mind is there to organize the
nomina
the things in themselves but it has a
phenomenological experience of the
things in themselves
okay and that then hands
the modern enlightenment a basic model
of a subjective phenomena
that is in some categorical relationship
with the nominal things in themselves
right
right okay okay and and that basically
you know that how dualistic that is it's
not really philosophical dualism but the
relationship between
phenomena and nomina is a very very
complicated
issue right right okay so now what we
want to do okay so now
we'll sort of fast forward that that
takes us into uh the 19th century
all right where science by this time
newton's work is really now it's
expanding into chemistry
um the the drive not the drive to
for scientific mathematical uh analysis
of matter and motion various kinds of
energy matter changes
is really i mean this is the heyday
right i mean people are making
discoveries that great things are
happening
okay and then what you get then is
the idea that well maybe we can
scientifically correspond
changes in the physical environment to
changes in
our phenomenological experience and to
do that
to yoke that together that would set the
stage for
systematic and science of the secondary
qualia
right right right right so like people
like fechner and people like that is
that
bingo that's exactly where we're going
okay so now helmholtz and fechner set
the stage
uh and generate some of actually the
most powerful and sustaining
findings okay the psychophysical laws of
just noticeable difference
okay absolute threshold and what they're
doing is they're
changing the relationship of a physical
stimulus in a
quantifiable primary quality way okay
and then they're having people report on
the changes in what it is that they
experience what just noticeable
differences they have
and what is the threshold of detection
and then what how do you make the change
physically and what pops up uh in a
person's field of first person
experience
so let's just give a quick example of
that i think that's very good
uh so one might be just notable's not
just noticeable difference
um so i have a sound which is a you know
wave frequency uh you know and i can
vary that
and i'm varying it physically right the
frequency
and then i ask people when they notice a
change in pitch
what i do is i figure out and then what
i do is uh i
i sort of measure out these changes in
pitch
against you know the continuous
variation
uh frequency of the wave and then i
calculate some
correspondence ratio between them and
then i get a psycho
physical law i get the psychological
event of noticing the difference
matched into uh where on the physical
continuum
of change in frequency that gets marked
and i get these
physical laws exactly exactly that's
exactly right
and what i want to then hone in as sort
of like when we use the term physical
we're going to have a very clear
reference point for what the physical
means
okay the problem of psychology is the
competing paradigms are
not going to um agree on what we just
used as the term
psychological right there right right
okay
because what we mean by there is exactly
this distinction between the primary and
secondary
and that is the grammar that emerges at
this juncture
okay so well i'm sorry i'm just gonna
say so one of the fundamental problems
then
is that the way uh given what we've
talked about the previous
classes uh sessions is that
the i mean the the very definition of
these
of these two types so the primary are by
definition
mathematically measurable and the
secondary ones are by definition
not mathematically measurable so how can
you possibly
measure them together exactly exactly
and and then we can start to think okay
so now what we see
is then this does establish the
fundamental trajectory
for what becomes psychology okay all
right so wilhelm vunt
is the father of psychology in general
all right and he picks up
on the psychophysics okay and we have
the psychophysics of sensation and what
he's going to do
is he's going to transform this into the
introspection
on perception okay
so i'll say that so you have the
psychophysical
around sensation so i'm going to jump
and then all you need to do is say oh i
feel that i notice the difference
okay now we're going to take it up a
layer
and i'm going to have a narrator an
introspectionist
report on what i see so if i hold up
this and you say well what do you see
i see a phone okay and then there's
going to be well actually is that what
you see is you see a phone or do you see
a shape that you then infer to be a
phone
okay so now we're going to have the now
what happens is well psychology
requires us to introspect and to share
about
this representational system that we
only have access to our own
internal world right right and and that
also is bringing up
the beginning of the problem of meaning
and intelligibility
because seeing it a phone
is not an entity which within
the ontology of physics physics talks
about mass
and it talks about but this being a
phone is not part
of that ontology properly okay so that's
oh thank god you bring that up okay so
now what
what one of the things that we're doing
here is where the
modern empirical natural science system
brings an epistemology we're going to
shift from your subjective perspective
to as external focus on the primary qual
quantities really as possible okay and
we're going to have a classical
mechanical
cause effect deterministic sequence that
is the
fundamental real ontology okay
of cause and effect and everything else
is sort of epiphenomenal potentially if
you're a hardcore reductive determinist
mechanical materialist right right right
okay so there's an ontological and
epistemological
language game that classical matter in
motion mechanics offers
and we're trying to then take that and
we're going to try to
understand the mind jammed into that
okay but there's going to be a lot of
debate as to whether well are we taking
the epistemology
of of that system or the ontology of
that
system yeah right right okay so the idea
is are we using
the methods of like newtonian science to
understand the mind
and human exemplifies this that's how he
understands what he's doing
or are we actually are we actually
landmark free
are we actually claiming that ultimately
the mind is just another
material thing that it is the thing it
is ultimately made out of
material stuff and exactly there's lots
of equivocation
between those two also yep going all
over the place okay so massive
so here we have and so what vant is vons
ontology is actually
psychophysical parallelism okay which
would be an actual early version of what
i would offer in some ways in the sense
that
it's he doesn't know how to connect the
two but he argues that they are
connected they're all one substance at
one level but there is some
fundamental cause effect relation at
some level that he hasn't unable to
specify so he wants to pull that out
okay uh but he's more interested in the
laboratory descriptive analysis of
professional introspectionists on their
inner experience
depending on the different environments
and and external
independent variables that they try to
share okay
so that's vant vund also makes a very
important point that he differentiates
the lab-based uh analysis of
inner experience versus what he calls
vulcar psychology which really sort of a
social
cultural folk psychology yeah okay
that term is used in cognitive science
right still so
okay yeah so basically for him he's like
well people are reporting on their
introspective experience all the time
they're generating narrative this is
it's going to drive art it's going to
drive convention
you can't experimentally analyze it but
if we understand the phenomenological
experiences
through introspection systematically
then we can understand the parts and
that's going to be part of psychology
and that's going to bridge us into the
other social sciences so that's vent
okay and and he uh to really
label him in a particular way we can
follow especially in american psychology
will follow his student edward titchener
okay and he brings to cornell university
he brings structuralism
all right and this is a he's an
authoritarian guy and he brings this
very strict
uh narrow view that psychology is only
about
human first-person experience and you
can only study it through his structure
and he developed and it is all about the
qualia he develops a list of
like 44 000 different possible qualia
that he then you know creates a
hierarchy of how they're organized okay
so so now psychology is the science for
this branch
of the structure of qualia right right
right okay
so did he i this is something i know
nothing of so this is a question out of
ignorance
i mean around the same time uh you're
you're getting the beginnings of
pragmatism
and you're also going to get you know
what's going to become phenomenology
in which people are trying to study a
phenomenological experience but i take
it that
i didn't i've never heard of any
connection between
people like uh host role and kitchener
or anything like that
or or i i wouldn't i don't know whether
titus was influenced or what he said
about
uh phenomenology exactly uh there's a i
think he predates it i think
yeah yeah well but there are what your
point about pragmatism and james
actually is nice i'll follow that line
okay because because that's actually
that's what then this is the first real
divide
in understanding what we mean by the
mental the psyche
okay okay so as you know um
we get william james who is one of the
fathers of pragmatism
okay and a philosopher and the father of
american psychology who writes in 1918
1890 principles of psychology okay
which is arguably in this time period as
far as i'm concerned the best book
written
in psychology okay it's like it's like
heads and shoulders really above the
rest in terms of what i think we'll come
back to
okay but here's james he's a pragmatist
and a functionalist which is the
functionalist wants to look around
and ask how the heck do animals and
humans
do what they do and in the world
okay and what is it about them that
enables them to behave
so radically differently than the
inanimate world the function
of their action okay which for james is
this is a
this will create a is mediated by
conscious mental life right right sorry
so james is uh influenced i know james
is somebody i study quite deeply
james is deeply influenced by darwin
right
exactly that's where the so the notion
of
i just want to be clear here for people
the notion gains functionalism is not
the same thing as computational
functionalism
no for james functionalism basically
means
something that explains darwinian
adaptation
exactly about that and then that also
introduces an important point here
that you know the darwini the darwinian
model um looks very
much like it fits into newtonian
worldview very well
uh you know it looks like you're just
talking about you know mechanic purely
mechanical processes
et cetera et cetera but it does
introduce and this is part of the
argument i make
it does introduce dynamical systems and
complex system theory
it it insinuates it into the newtonian
worldview
um and people sensitive people thought
for people like james
were picking up on this right in which i
think it's fair to say
the physicists at the time were not
picking up on
uh on that that's a great point okay so
now let's back up
just a second because this is a this is
exactly what is happening
in terms of the meta what i call the
descriptive metaphysical problem that we
get ourselves into
okay so if we go back to galileo we
mentioned this earlier i
i you know offered you were commenting
that and i reiterated
so galileo hates metaphysics okay and he
and much of his identity is breaking
from aristotle across the entire
aristotle
four causes of substance material
uh kinetic efficient okay and then you
have
formal and final causation all right
and you matter in motion as the words
imply
require some sort of substance and some
sort of kinetic
but the rest of it is a shoot okay and i
believe that the material dimension of
complexity if you you know in my
language system of the trillion dollars
is the matter dimension
yeah actually um aristotle's application
of final and formal causation
to the behavior of atoms and rocks is
not as superfluous and confusing and not
very effective
but when you get into what plants
uh cells even animals and people are
doing
we're talking about a radically
different set of behaviors
okay that are both a function of
something very different
and they function really it's hard to
not see them as functioning
to do different things right you get
this function
of and then function two dynamic exactly
and what what what i
what i want to do just to connect that
back
is the notion of adaptivity exactly
smuggles those two
in because you have to talk about the
structural functional organization
and what it functions to do it functions
to afford the organism
surviving long enough to successfully
reproduce so these these are
aristotelian and you know
alicia gerardo has noted this
darwin is basically smuggling in i don't
think in any explicit fashion
but he's bringing in dynamical systems
he's bringing in deep continuity
he but he's bringing in as gregor said
he's smuggling in
uh these two missing aristotelian causes
absolutely and i believe that actually
when we get sophisticated about the
concept of information uh computational
process all of that
we are then going to see exactly what is
the functional information processing
storage accumulation over the
generations
how it gets played out in an
individual's life of course they don't
have access to these concepts at this
juncture
right um but genetics the computational
science revolution et cetera all of that
will then
uh awaken us to these other ways of
thinking
uh that are that are not available but
so james is a functionalist he's a he's
also gives rise to radical empiricism
by which he he wants to embrace hey what
do we see
what do we actually see in the world and
what is our functional
useful explanations for how it actually
works and the real mystery for
him is is really what i would call sort
of a mental life
behavioral view and what he means by
that is he's watching the actions and
adaptations
of animals across their life and
understanding the darwinian history of
it
and says that's the dynamic functional
mental life psychology should be
explaining how the hell that happens
that's what our task is
and to sit in a lab and nitpick
structural differences between qualia
is not where the problem's at right
right right right right right
well said very well okay so there's a
sense in which
the two problems that are the subtitle
of our our
work together are really coming together
in james right there
and the tension between the
functionalists and the structuralists
right and we get then this break so you
ha and this is a very strong break the
structuralist especially by the time
titchener comes along
he's like this is what you do and you
either submit to me or you're you're
doing something different and i want to
own psychology okay
and james of course has already been
influenced and so they
they are not uh agreeing okay on what it
is that they're talking about
right and then in the uh right at the
now
the 20th century it's about the time so
james is published 1890. i don't
remember exactly when titurnary gets
installed in cornell but
you know 1905 1910s that's the dynamic
well then another thing happens actually
two things that will happen
simultaneously to give us
the split across all these domains and
we will then have a
by 1920s we will have the ossified
problem of psychology which the great
theorist russian theorist lev vygotsky
calls the crisis
okay so we're heading towards the crisis
all right
right let's keep going so and then we
have two major figures that
in american psychology then set the
stage for the dominant paradigms that
are operative in american
we get watson watson comes along
and and is wants to be is working with
animals and his experimentalist
okay so he's in the lab he wants a
framework for understanding
the methodology of experimentism he
wants the epistemology of natural
science
and he is a hardcore mechanical
reductionist
okay so he has the entire he wants to
then bring
the physical science methods of
experimentation epistemology of external
observation
and the idea that basically everything
is matter in motion
and for him a complex of neuromechanical
reflexes
yeah he's deeply influenced by both
pavlov and thorndike right the oil
exactly
uh he is right particularly pavlov
why because at the time in particular
now skitter will advance on this
at the time the pavlovian reflexology
that pavlov was developing
okay for those who don't pavlov is
actually a digestive and physiological
person but in russia the categories are
a little different
he's tech he's testing how meat powder
attacks
uh results in salivation and dogs most
commonly
he develops this unbelievably powerful
paradigm which is with us today
classical conditioning although it's
it's been updated so we know kind of
more functionally what it's going on
in relationship to learning but it's a
pairing of a bell
classically with meat powder boom and
then the bell gives rise to salivation
okay and now you can test this and this
is conforms
to the language game of natural
experimental science
we have independent variables there's a
mechanistic process we have dependent
variables
we can now begin the serious process
of real psychology because we know that
everything is just
physical anyway and so we're just it's
just a complicated matrix of physical
switches and now we have a methodology
according to the classic behavioral
system of a stimulus response and he's
very explicit get rid of consciousness
okay it doesn't work in the language
game but what we can study is now he's
an introduces
officially behavior mind as
behavior you don't need the concept of
mind what you do need is the concept of
behavior
so everything now in psychology is in
terms of
observable measurables can measure the
physical properties of the stimulus
and then i can measure the physical
response of the organism
and that's all i'll need in order to
explain behavior of course is
he's the father of behaviorism exactly
exactly
so and then that becomes a very very
powerful mind notice it because it lines
up with the epistemology ontology
and methods of physics okay so
that's and then uh what's happening in a
very parallel time in vienna
uh a guy by the name of sigmund freud
okay he's actually
at the time working as a neurologist
okay early on
uh and studying crabs and other
crustaceans and
finds hey this nervous system thing it's
all about
activation and inhibition okay
everything is activation and inhibition
and of course the steam engine has been
enormously influential in terms of
so is this nervous system thing
uh a energy release kind of mechanism
right right so and and then he shows how
hey experiences can be shown he's
actually as early models of long-term
potentiation are found in his work and
he starts initially
a project for scientific psychology
which he never publishes
okay um but for him then now we have the
idea that out of the nervous system is
going to be energies
all right but then he hooks up um
with a number of people but basically to
focus
what he start he needs to make a living
and he hooks up into a physician
practice
and starts to look at how people are
getting hypnotized
okay um and what he what notices
at the time is an appreciation that
some people will have a complete change
in their physical symptoms
uh when they're hypnotized and most
commonly or classically what's called
glove amnesia and there's a syndrome of
the time
so somebody would not have any feeling
in their hand okay
they could prick it they could look away
blah blah and
freud knew enough and they knew enough
about neuro anatomy
at the time to know that actually that
doesn't make any sense from a
neuro-anatomy perspective because
actually
you'll feel this if your hand goes to
sleep sometimes these two fingers are
tied to one nerve
and these the rest of your hands tied to
another the idea that you would have a
a line right there that would lead to
numbness is really odd
okay and then somebody would be
hypnotized and all of a sudden they'd
have some cathartic moment
and this is right about the time and
freud's getting these kinds of terms
and then they'd release and all of a
sudden ah the hand feels
again so freud sees a couple of these
instances
and and then transforms his idea of
energy impulse that the nervous system
in general
is that's underneath okay the conscious
rationales that we are giving okay
and and what's actually happening with a
lot of chaos confusion
is that there's this massive
misdirection of consciousness for reason
giving
relative to these animalistic urges and
impulses
and they start leaking out through the
filter of consciousness
and he does interpretation of dreams and
then in 1899 right before the turn of
the century
he then does um psychopathology in
everyday life in 1904
okay he then gets invited in the clark
lectures in 1909 i think it is
i think he comes with young at that
stage and
introduces by this time he has this
analysis that
hey folks conscious reasoning and
self-conscious awareness that's the tip
of the iceberg okay
huge amounts of suffering confusion and
the ultimate drivers of human behavior
are these animalistic biological drives
that we are unaware of okay and they
drive a lot
and so he so now what is he concerned
with the dynamic unconscious that which
is
behind consciousness okay very which
then puts him at odds a bit with james
and doesn't have a real good model for
the distinction between uh
sub or non-conscious process versus
consciousness okay
he's aligned with watson in some ways
and that's a hydraulic model but it's
unbelievably mentalistic
okay and freud does drop his strong
mechanistic reductionism it gives rise
to psychic determinism
in the sense that there is a psychic
energy his ontology of it isn't very
clear
but fundamentally what we then have is
so now we have
let's just review we have the attempt to
scientifically analyze
the mind okay which is then
sort of defined originally in sort of
the dominant idea of the day that is
these secondary experiences relative to
primary events psychophysics starts down
that road
you get then the emergence of um
uh vunt and then the structuralist line
off of titchener
okay so that's one meaning of psyche all
right
then we have the adaptive mental life
functional meaning from james
all right then we have no that really
psyche to the extent that means anything
it's just what
animals do that we can experimentally
analyze
all right then finally it's no there's
an underlying mental
psychic entity that we're not fully
conscious of we have a conscious filter
system
it leaks out there's a dynamic
unconscious and this we need to study it
and what freud also offers that the
other three don't is he offers
uh a comparatively effective form of
therapy
exactly so you so you get this he wants
psychoanalysis to be a science of the
unconscious
a treatment for neurosis and ultimately
a world
view that understands civilization and
humans discontent
and of course he's of all the people in
terms of the impact freud is a
you know head and shoulders above in
terms of because he spills over to the
humanities and he just
um he's such an unbelievable gigantic
whatever you think of him his influences
um surpassed only by you know einstein
and a few other people and
that's one of the issues at least but
but that success
is actually the opposite of what becomes
an increasing
form of criticism of freud which is
freud's model doesn't fit in to the
scientific worldview
and it doesn't you can't study it with
scientific methodology
that's right that's the popularity and
critique of it now i
i find that you know his ideas are so
complex and actually
we know that a lot of them are wrong
precisely because we can systematically
analyze them so
i find poppers critique a little
simplistic in some ways but you're
i mean uh yeah um but you're absolutely
right the question of
what freud's ideas are and whether they
are scientific or not
he said is a you know one of the great
and i certainly he way overshoots and
comes up with a number of crazy things
that can't be falsified so there's
definitely aspects of his ideas that are
very difficult to falsify
and they basically become sort of
objects of faith um
that the psychoanalytic faithful uh
pledge allegiance to
that's well said but it's well said um
and then that
that's gonna be a problem that's gonna
ramble through
um all the i mean let's maybe we could
pause here and say
what are what are the problems that each
one have so the problem with freud is
uh and the whole psychodynamics it also
applies to young is
well what's like what's the epistemology
here and how does this fit into the
scientific world view
is this even a science at all is this a
science of the mind
even though it's very clinically
effective
right and then the problem facing watson
of course which is going to be the
endemic problem of behaviorism
right and this is going to derive what's
called the cognitive revolution is
and you can hear you can hear james over
here it's because organisms
and this is what actually comes out of
the more sophisticated study of
pavlovian and upward condition
these organisms ultimately don't respond
to the physical property of the stimulus
they respond to the meaning of the
stimulus so
just to give a very common example
an organism can see the light colored
light of a fire
it can smell the smoke right and those
are two very different physical things
but it responds in exactly the same way
because they mean
the same adaptive thing to the organism
and so it's going to be one of the so
the meaning is missing
uh from behaviorism the problem with
structuralism and titchener and
introspectionism is
right for all of his and you're
completely right for all of his
authoritarian taxonomy
you just don't get the invariant
agreement you want introspection just
is too um it's well it's too beset
by all of the bakeries of
human consciousness and working memory
and self-deception and bias
and then the problem with with for for
james
right and i think of all of all of them
james saw his own problems maybe better
than others
absolutely i think james realized that
trying to incorporate these darwinian
ideas into the study of mind was
problematic given the standard cartesian
epistemology
that's why he becomes so enamored
um with pierce first right yep
pragmatism because pragmatism is an
attempt
to create uh an alternative epistemology
an alternative to cartesian mathematical
epistemology
exactly the degree to which that project
uh has succeeded of course is
problematic
so that's how why that's why it's still
uh it's still an issue
uh dan chappie and i are reading uh
bacon's book
on pragmatism which is traces this here
this history of
um ongoing like when you get to
especially
get to figures like quine and davidson
and sellers already
the ongoing you know dialogue and debate
between pragmatism and and
scientism which is a cartesian
interpretation of how you do science
um and that's that's that so that
problem is ongoing
so quick review so not only are we
getting fragmentation it looks like
each one of these four is in some
important sense lacking definitely
lacking inadequate
definitely lacking and so and somewhat
from just a basic
we can we should be able in my opinion
we should be able to step back
things will get a little complicated
with the cognitive revolution but we can
basically sit back and say okay
so you have some people saying uh mind
is just behavior
okay all right and then you have someone
saying hey
mind is phenomenology right right okay
uh you have that
and then you have sort of some sort of
functional cognitive mental life with
james
right right right and then you have this
distinction between
a self-conscious portion of mind and a
sober unconscious portion and the
dynamic relation between them
in freud yeah and freud okay these are
the referent points
okay and i think we should be able a a
unified frame of psychology we'll be
able to
put the ontological reference in each of
those that there is a way to think about
mind
and behavior is connected okay there is
a way to think about
phenomenology there is a way to think
about the hierarchy of consciousness in
a self-conscious into subconscious kind
of dimension
okay and we're going to want a an
adequate unified frame of psychology
will conceptually juxtapose these
ontological reference into a consilient
picture right so
that of course and that's going to be
something we're going to work towards
that's what we're working towards that
we're just
right now what we should all in terms of
problem formulation we're still in the
problem for emulation stage the history
of ideas that are competing
and once again what what somebody's
observing this conversation observing
this history is like
there's no adequate language game
there's just no adequate language game
there's no adequate one but there's also
four that are competing with you yeah
absolutely right there's no adequate
super ordinate one
they're reasonable if you enter into it
and you say hey i'm gonna start playing
this game
they obviously live because they have
slices of information
that have reasonable things to say that
you can start gaining cumulative
knowledge around
absolutely you know but at the same time
they are totally the
the rules and grammar by which they play
force definitions and are limited when
you flip outside of them and they
compete and they say oh so watson's most
obvious about this he just has to say
you can't talk about consciousness it's
pointless it's outside
the modern empirical natural science
language game period
so there it is so you're you violate the
rules as soon as you bring
the term in right so let's let's gather
this all together because it's
really important so we get a host
of what let's call them epistemological
and metaphysical problems
from descartes and the scientific
revolution which we've already explored
and then what happens is you get the
birth of
a science or at least the proto-science
that's
posted in some sense solve this address
this
right somehow situate mind back in the
scientific worldview
project but when it tries to do this
right not only does it not
adequately address the cartesian
problems given to us
uh like the epistemological and
metaphysical problems given to us by the
by descartes in the scientific
revolution it it now introduces this
additional problem
which we may call it i don't know what
to call it we could call it
um like a disciplinary problem in the
sense of
what we have or a paradigmatic problem
or something like that
i want to distinguish it from the pure
sort of epistemological and metaphysical
yeah no it's
it's a it's a it's a multiple it's kind
of like uh i'll use uh peter lindberg's
notion of
culture war 2.0 it's the explosion
of multi-polarity okay and they're
trying to compete then for paradigmatic
attention and dominance and resource
where they then have to deploy uh
critiques of others and
and it is a very much a hey what side
are you
on what group are you going to be so
that's going to create the amount of
both equivocation defense it's not
they're not engaged india logos here
to get to the answer they are generally
engaged in staking out territory and
trying to get attention and resources
which of course that adds enormous
amount
of chaos and uncertainty in relationship
to what it is that
you know we are talking about right so
when you so
when you turn let's say you want to try
and address the problems that descartes
has between
us and then you say what i do is i'll
turn to science and gather data and good
theory
in order to try and come up with a way
of solving these cartesian problems
instead what you get is this fragmented
mess
right that that actually right
is thwarting your ability to give an
adequate
even an adequate problem formulation of
what descartes
has left us right i i talked to somebody
again sort of more on the science side
of this equation but coming from complex
that actually is jim rutt
i was talking to him the other day he's
like well i looked into psychology and i
i couldn't make heads or tails of it
so that on the and i've talked to a
number of philosophers sort of in the
same way it's like
you enter into it you enter into the
swamp of
of all of this kind of possible angles
data sets language games etc okay
and and so by 1927 lev vygotsky
you know who tragically dies early but
he's a brilliant psychologist
he's second only to piaget in terms of
developmental psychology
oh absolutely yeah like vygotsky is is
is an unrecognized titan right right
um one of my next door uh right next to
me and we hired her
is elaine of a savina she is a russian
psychologist educational psychologist
got both
her doctorate in russian psychology and
doctorate in american school psychology
so
um we have thankfully an expert in
vygotsky in theory right next door so
it's nice
but so yeah and actually um we could do
a whole nother issue about what happens
in russia
and what gives rise to what's called
russian activity theory okay
which actually is similar to foreign
cognition and
a contextual adaptive behavior dynamic
system that's really fascinating with a
layered
cultural uh tool language tool structure
that develops in context it's brilliant
okay
but american psychology that's not what
happens in american psychology
it's actually anglo-american psychology
by this point too isn't it
yeah yes absolutely uh and so that's a i
want to be clear that
i'm trailing but the problem is super
interesting even when we circle
uh the particular cultural context for
it okay
so we have to remember england and
america are going to be the next two
superpowers
that's right they dominate the world in
a very important way
that's right and and they and they have
this very strong empiricist bent
okay um that actually has all sorts of
power
but at the same time empiricism in and
of itself if you don't have the concepts
and categories can't get you
out you have to have logic or
metaphysical clarity descriptive
metaphysical clarity
um to actually gain cumulative knowledge
okay so
i interrupted you you're going to say
what luria said sorry what the glotsky
said
right so vygotsky the point i want to
make is that vygotsky has identified
exactly what i'm telling you i was going
to say that actually he says you know
if you pay attention actually it's not
even the theorists that are really
articulating what the issue is
it's practitioners it's psychiatrists by
the mid 1920s
everyone's like i don't know what
psychology is there's no general frame
is it freud
is it watson uh there was an emergence
of personalism
uh the personalist approach by wilhelm
stern at the time
and that actually builds off of you know
sort of combines a few
and and and he's in gestalt psychology
but they actually all line to the
uh domains that i've identified up to
this point
okay logical and functional right
exactly and and so now
boom you get this real crisis all right
um and
and russian activity theory offers i
think actually uh um
not the exact same solution that i do
but an interesting one but inside
american empiricism
the the system simply grows okay so
in terms of its confusion right so you
get
here's a couple of other pieces that
then emerge then in the
uh in england and in particular united
states so out of watson
you get skinner yes okay skinner is not
a classic behaviorist
okay he's a radical behaviorist
and has his whole philosophy of what
behaviorism is and absolutely
for him what everything we call mind is
behavior
right okay for skinner so he's like
you're always in the presence of one
behaving person
if you have a toothache that is part of
that is your manifestation of private
behavior
okay so the complete uh transition of
the language of what
normally would be called mind is called
behavior the goal of science is the
prediction and control of behavior
and skinner gives rise to um a branch of
that
okay which i think is absolutely crucial
to understand it's
wrong in some ways it's unbelievably
it's defined against the information
processing view
of the cognitive revolution okay which
we'll come back to in a sec
um but it is absolutely crucial that we
better have a framework for mind as
behavior okay in my opinion and gilbert
ryall as a philosophical i was just
going to bring up
he's going to be like i think makes the
very important point that our categories
about what we think about his mind
much of it is behavior and what what the
unified theory ultimately lends me to
is that actually we need to instantiate
the concept of
mental behavior okay mental behavior
turns to be a very very complex
important bridging concept between our
fractured systems that can then be
organized
okay so we get skinner and that's
important for our own confusion because
a number about five to ten percent of
psychologists to this day think about
psychology as the science of behavior
not a behavior and mental process okay
so and and it gives rise to this
powerful but also very isolating
radical behavioral view that's it that's
diametrically
opposed to a number of other paradigms
so it is a radical
paradigmatic view and and hardcore
behaviors you know
people outside of their culture will be
like god you can't talk to those people
yeah but so let's let's i mean so while
uh is important because he so um
within cockside i was taught to
distinguish between skinner's
methodological behaviorism and rile's
logical behaviorism
um but they're they're allies uh and
like
uh rao famously argued that all mental
terms can be
are logically analyzable into basically
multi-track dispositional terms
right classic example is belief um we
think because it's a verb that we should
be looking for some
mental event and while says no all
you're doing is expressing a conditional
behavior um to say i believe the
training is to say if i see
the windows open i will close it right
or if i go outside i'll take an umbrella
etc and then what what skinner's doing
with the methodological behavior is
what's giving that what's what's keeping
behaviorism
going in my opinion is
what did david get back and say at one
point a hundred thousand
hours of experimentation the
behaviorists really
really develop experimental methodology
to a very significant degree they
definitely do
right and and i and i think that
skinner's concept of behavioral
selection okay
is really very powerful when you when
you understand
the tren the evolution from the classic
stimulus response pairing
into a feedback loop okay
of behavioral what i would call
behavioral investments
that have differential consequences that
then select
pathways of investment yeah and i just
want to highlight that because
and other people have noted this that
this is something that people within 40
cogs i have noted
that that's uh that's skinner slipping
darwin in
oh uh yeah and actually he right he he
wasn't and skinner if you read him i
mean he didn't slip it in he's like i
want to be the darwin
of opera in theory that's what he said
you're right for correcting me greg
i didn't i i gave uh i my connotation
was incorrect
uh what i meant is um skinner
in fact often explicitly refers to
darwin
right if you leave textbooks on skinner
you're absolutely right yeah yeah
right right right absolutely so and
skinner some skinner wants to understand
us in this conversation okay as a
functional response across
three different tiers of selection okay
natural selection operand selection and
verbal selection
right okay that's his model which by the
way is going to translate immediately
well natural selection gives rise to the
complex dynamic interplay of life
behavioral selection gives us to the
complex dynamic interplay of
animal behavior which i call mine and
then
verbal selection justification of rules
grammars constituencies
give rise to so he then has this very
conte
he's a contextualist not a mechanist
okay that is fundamental if you're
familiar with steven piffer's uh world
views okay
in 1942 argued these different
fundamental so uh
uh watson is a mechanist through and
through skinner's a contextualist okay
he's always putting things in context
it's really really fascinating
um but anyway so yeah so now what you
get but
but the the horror of this okay is that
because he
then insists with this behavioral
tradition
we're not integrating sophisticated
operand theory or at least we're
vulnerable to breaking off sophisticated
operant theory from the cognitive models
yes okay and it's the 4e people that
have we got to come back
decades later right to reintegrate and
embodied enacted think of
the terms embodied the enacted the
extended
all right this is this is the nervous
system in dynamic relation
with the environmental contingencies
okay but it gets split off
uh and and it and it and it forces a
particular kind of language
that's that's one thing skinner is he's
unbelievably hostile to mentalism
he's very um so that's uh
that's gonna that's gonna be to some
degree
his achilles heel because precisely
because he reaches up to the level
of verbal selection he's gonna slam into
chomsky
right and this is gonna be this is gonna
be the devastating
the devastating defeat of his career in
so many ways
he's been allowed and rightfully so so
here's according
in the sense that so you have then uh so
then the humanists happened by the way
and i'm not going to get into them but
we have obviously
uh maslow and uh and which become
unbelievably crucial for the identity of
psychology
rightfully so but also when we get into
the profession
okay and what we are and what we're
trying to help people with and whether
these other models are really
deterministic and nasty
so this third force um is crucial for
human potential it's crucial for
how to like actually have people be
helpful in context
so that's a very important thing but the
science of before you turn from it greg
i just want to put a little flag in
there
uh that maslow is also bringing back
aristotle in a very powerful yes
if needs is barrier absolutely it's a
very scale of nature kinds of stuff in
many ways
uh so um and so maybe when we come back
to
and certainly i consider the meta
psychology i built a scientific
humanistic philosophy
okay so and i'm as a and as a absolutely
crucial
to understand the application and
professional development of psychology
and there are a lot of really powerful
ideas uh that rogers has
about the science of argue of human
beings definitely
um i was just a little conscious of time
and i want to sort of make sure we wrap
this up in relationship to the
uh get to the revolution yeah yeah so
so and you and i know this very well so
we'll just sort of summarize so
then uh you go back to babbage babbage
builds a difference engine
okay and we get a the emergence of the
idea of a thinking machine we alluded to
some of that
all right and then it's in the 1920s
into 1930s and then explodes in the 40s
and 50s
okay that the world of information
science and theory and mechanisms
pop okay they explode okay
basically exactly you get the turing
revolution where you get shannon's
emphasis on information as reduction
uncertainty give rise to information
theoretic approaches
okay which has become unbelievably
influential basically
um for those that are not aware his i
his notions about certainty chaos order
disorder
basically overlap completely it turns
out with thermodynamics
so yeah that's a really fascinating
reality there and we'll come back by the
way in the unified system
uh to be a very important thing because
entropy and energy and the free energy
accumulation inside and out turns out to
be a very very
key element okay um so what we get
is i mean so what greg is doing and he's
he's introducing something that's going
to be
sort of uh the progenitor of cognitive
science right you've got it you're
getting the beginning and turing
proposes it right the imitation game etc
the possibility of a new way of studying
mine
but study mind by making minds and i
mean
let's build artificial intelligence and
and
we will we will go around all of this
chaos in psychology
and what we'll do is we'll build it and
because we built it we know how it works
and then and what and then and we can
also we can we
can start talking uh we have a way of
talking about the mental
that doesn't seem sort of spooky and
weird the way watson and skinner don't
like
because we could what's gonna this is a
bit anachronistic
going backwards but we'll be able to
talk about the hardware versus the
software
of these information processing machines
and
the hardware is where the mechanical
language goes and the software is where
the mental languages go and then wow
this will be this
and then of course that's going on as
greg
said and then chomsky is over here
talking
showing that skinner can't explain
language
at all and then what seems to be
coming to into the fore with the
computational revolution is the idea
of computer languages programs and
computer languages
and that that is the way in which we'll
be able to explain language
and cognition and it looks like the
promise of a great
uh reunification that's outside of all
of this chaos
that greg has um has
uh indicated so it's a 100 and so that's
a
and that and to the extent that
psychology does get organized that's
exactly
what happens in some ways okay but uh
but so
so we get this but there's all this
equivocation and
totally inside the system but yes so
crucially folks okay
information information theoretic
information semantic and information
processing i make a distinction between
those
three layers of this but they but but
they're equivocating at this juncture
but now what we do have
is we have an idea that's consistent in
many ways
with the natural science it is very
consistent in many ways
although i would argue the cause effect
of information
processing information theoretic
especially that's then directed
through a semantic system towards
something this is where you get this is
descriptively these are different kinds
of cause effect behavior yeah yeah
they are and i i would supplement that
by saying
that what's called good old-fashioned ai
the computational approach
is and this is it leaves out what you
were just flagging what was good in
skinner that whole dynamical system
selection model
that the computational system the
computational approach
really misses all of that selectivity
that dynamical coupling
right they they jumped on the
algorithmic processing so fast
and then the building of it so fast that
they acted as though they could just
extract it completely it was so powerful
at one level there's so much excitement
they left the body they left evolution
they left actual phenomenological
perception
you know participatory knowing and the
actual embodiment of procedures they
left all that crap behind
and acted they could just you know well
big you know deep blue beats people at
chess so that must be the whole damn
thing
yeah yeah exactly exactly right okay
so well i was just going to say so the
the
i mean there's there's a sense in which
um i'm just going to speak as a clock
side and i'll give the mic back to you
like cockside promises to try and deal
with these problems
but but that it hasn't yet produced
a solution to the mess of
the science of the mind is that fair to
say 100
uh and in fact we still we it helps okay
so the cognitive piece is absolutely
central
all right we need to understand that the
nervous system is there for a reason
it's taking up energy
and fundamentally just like your gut
digests food to distribute energy the
nervous system digests information
right right it digests information and
we didn't know
that before okay so the cognitive really
so now like searle to
making a reference here to cyril is a
biological emphasize sort of
yeah it digests information it processes
information it metabolizes information
now how it does that and what we
actually mean by those terms
okay is is enormously complicated and
how we embody that back into all these
other domains of psychology
right exactly exactly okay so the
functionality of mental life the actual
structure of phenomenology
and mindless behavior okay either in an
experimental condition or in an
adapter beautifully said that's
beautifully said
okay so so what is actually we're
looking at
right now so essentially what modern
psychology is is it's a collection of
all that crap
okay it has a completely equivocating
cognitive mental process that's some
sort of functional information
processing
thing okay with five percent of
psychologists still holding
strong to skinner all right with all of
these different paradigms around it and
then they say hey it's the science of
behavior and mental process but the key
thing is we do science
that's how textbooks are and they never
tell you we actually well this is what
we mean by
mine this is what we mean by behavior
and this is the scientific language game
that we are playing
that's and we don't know how to define
those terms
hence an enormous and uh completely
unsatisfactory language system
and thus the pre multi-paradigmatic mess
and then cognitive science comes along
and says okay well we'll take care of it
i'm like well good luck
yeah no for sure
the thing is cognitive science was
supposed to be the solution to
fragmentation
but there's also fragmentation within
cognitive science between the
computational evidence well now we're
getting
consciousness studies right i don't know
there's a whole like the arizona career
there's consciousness studies
the entire system and that's the that's
the issue is is that we've exploded
there's equivocation there's enormous
and then it's huge it's this
mass okay and then how do you create how
do you manage all of that inertia
and how do we understand what it is uh
and and so instead
uh to untie the world not we have to
understand that history
and and the task before us as far as i'm
concerned
is what will happen when it's done is a
unified field frame
okay that says oh i understand what they
were referring to
and their epistemology i understand how
each one of those domains were making
sense
and now conciliate wise we can make
sense of them all together there can be
a jumping together of facts
with coherence and clarity right
okay that's excellent and then the idea
is
that part of what we're doing is that
project is bound up
and in dialogue with the project that we
got sort of from descartes and
bobs right which is how you have to
right because
the hard problem of phenomenological
consciousness and its relationship to
conscious justification in humans and
embodiment and action
in animals down the line is unsolved
but if we there's some sort of we can
realize the relevance of a hierarchy
that results in something we could piece
this thing together and have a good
language system and that's what i sense
you to be
right on the trail of that's what yeah
that that's well said that's what we're
that's what we're trying to do right
here
break your work and might work together
on that i wanted to point out one other
thing and you and you
you uh there was an allusion to it um
uh there's one other way in which this
is problematic which is as you said
uh you said that um these texts i have a
third thing i'm gonna probably i'm gonna
make this worse
but i know it's already implicit in your
work so i want to explicate
it right these textbooks not only fail
to tell you what
mind is and what behavior is uh they
actually don't
tell you well they pro there's
pretension
in telling you what science is the
philosophy of science
that is presupposed in sort of textbook
psychology
is very very poor philosophy of science
the model of science there
like for example watson's uh what let's
just give one clear
quick example watson's idea that science
works only in terms of observables
and never in terms of unobservable
entities is just ridiculously false
i mean he's the point is he it's
anachronistic
because of the time in which he was
looking around and seeing science
but you know even by that time uh uh
scientists were
were pulling away from that model and
now of course
most of the entities that science talks
about are not
directly observable they're they're in
theoretically inferred
and right and so completely right
and that's not an exhaustive criticism
like this thing i mean no that's a
listen that's an example right it's an
unbelievable nightmare and
to me it's like okay we're gonna take
this thing called the scientific method
and
hey as long as you just follow that you
know then you get what the answer is and
man is there's nothing that we know more
clearly you don't just
cookie cutter okay yeah this method in
parrot it
and then yield as if it's a well-defined
problem that you just follow the little
recipes on and you get to the cake at
the end
that's not what this is and we in fact
know that it's not yet that's what
they're
taught i mean this is the third most cop
popular major
psych 101 is like one of the most
popular courses
and it provides no frame that what
they're being handed
i mean it took me a while really is
actually an enormous amount of
gobbledygook
at a conceptually sophisticated level so
so
so to me the problem of psychology both
is a very important understand
and it gets it gets into getting the
proper metaphysics of
ultimately of love of friendship of what
it is that we're trying to do in this
world
you know and and so that's the that's
the um why to me i'm so passionate about
helping people realize there's a real
we're we can just open your eyes see the
history and see it
right there there's really something
very important for us to try to uh
russell that's fantastic
okay i think we've now i think we've now
between these four sessions i think
we've really
set up um at least an initially good
problem i think we got the problem
formulation going
exactly i mean we're going to come back
to it because we're going to talk again
about things we've alluded to
like the you know the inadequacies of
gofi
first second third generation um uh
trying to reintegrate uh phenomenology
and functionality back into the science
of mind
that was a hallmark by the way of what's
called for e cox i
um instead of constantly sneaking
aristotle back in let's make it explicit
alicia gerardo dynamical systems theory
uh the
deep continuity hypothesis of evan toxin
these are all things we still have to
explore
uh but at least i think we've got the
beginnings of
a good problem formulation and a shared
language for doing that so thank you
great
that was absolutely great today that was
really good fantastic yes there's
clearly a world not here right
of consciousness mind behavior whatever
there's a world not
and i'm excited because i think that
there's enormous convergent validity
here
that allows that world not to be
potentially untangled so